Finding aid to the Inez Whipple Wilder Papers CA.MS.00405
Smith College Archives
Inez Whipple Wilder Papers
1871-1988
Smith College Archives
Wilder, Inez Whipple, 1871-1929
CA.MS.00405
0.833 linear feet (2 containers)
Contains news clippings, photographs, research and publications from Inez Whipple Wilder's professional papers.
Biographical / Historical
Inez Whipple Wilder was born in Diamond Hill, Rhode Island in 1871 to Eliab Daniel and Sarah (Wheaton) Whipple. She graduated from Rhode Island Normal School in 1890 and the in 1900 she received her Ph.B from Brown University. Wilder taught for several years at the Rhode Island State Normal School and at Northampton High School, until she joined the Smith College faculty in 1902. In 1904, Wilder received her A.M in biology. In 1906, Wilder married Professor Harris Hawthorne Wilder of the biology department who she worked alongside until his death in 1928, when she succeeded him as head of the department. While at Smith, Inez Wilder studied salamander morphology, as well as pioneering the study of finger prints. She died of a long illness in 1929.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the professional papers of Inez Whipple Wilder. These include some biographical information, like photographs and obituaries, but the majority of the collection is taken up by Wilder's numerous publications and by her research.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Wilder, Inez Whipple, 1871-1929
- The Manual of Phonography, 1886 (Box 1084, Folder 1)
- Notebook, 1909 (Box 1084, Folder 2)
- Collections, undated (Box 1084, Folder 3)
- Biographies: obituary, 1928-1988 (Box 1084, Folder 4)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1084, Folder 5)
- Publications: An Anomaly in the Portal Circulation of the Cat, 1919 (Box 1084, Folder 6)
- Publications: On the Breeding Habits of Desmognathus fusca, 1917 (Box 1084, Folder 7)
- Publications: The Correlation of the Lunglessness in Salamanders with Mountain Brook Habitat, undated (Box 1084, Folder 8)
- Publications: Lab Studies in Mammalian Anatomy, edition 1 and 2, 1914-1923 (Box 1084, Folder 9)
- Publications: Developmental History of Eurycea bislineata in Western Mass., 1924 (Box 1084, Folder 10)
- Publications: Hermaphorditism in Eurycea bislineata, 1924 (Box 1084, Folder 11)
- Publications: Life History of Desmognathus fusca, 1913 (Box 1084, Folder 12)
- Publications: The Morphology of the Palmar Digital Triradii and Main Lines, 1929-1930 (Box 1084, Folder 13)
- Publications: Morphology of Amphibian Metamorphosis, 1925 (Box 1084, Folder 14)
- Publications: The Naso-Labial Groove of Lungless Salamanders, 1906 (Box 1084, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1084, Folder 16)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--typscript, undated (Box 1085, Folder 1)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata, 1924 (Box 1085, Folder 2)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--illustrations, 1915 (Box 1085, Folder 3)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--computations and summaries, 1921-1922 (Box 1085, Folder 4)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--standard deviation of normal table data, undated (Box 1085, Folder 5)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--normal data, undated (Box 1085, Folder 6)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--comparison of weight and length, 1917-1922 (Box 1085, Folder 7)
- Publications: Relation of Growth Metamorphosis in Eurycea bislineata--tables removed, undated (Box 1085, Folder 8)
- Publications: On Copeia: Spermatophores of Desmoganthus fusca--, 1923 (Box 1085, Folder 9)
- Publications: Variations in the Premaxillary Eurycea bislineata, 1924 (Box 1085, Folder 10)
- Publications: The Ventral Surface of the Mammalian Chiridium, 1903 (Box 1085, Folder 11)
- Publications: The Ypsiloid Apparatus of Urodeles, 1906 (Box 1085, Folder 12)
- Publications: Abystoma drawings (miscellaenous), 1919-1925 (Box 1085, Folder 13)
- Publications: "Cold Spring Harbor" Studies of Eurycea bislineata--metamorphosis of the skull, 1919 (Box 1085, Folder 14)
- Publications: "Cold Spring Harbor" Studies of Eurycea bislineata--studies of individual bones, undated (Box 1085, Folder 15)
- Publications: Amphibia drawings (miscellaenous), 1916 (Box 1085, Folder 16)
- Publications: Eurycea bislineata Studies of External Form, especially of head, in Developmental Stage, 1916-1917 (Box 1085, Folder 17)
- Publications: Spelerpes (Eurycea) bislineata Naco-lacrimal duct enlargement--notes and drawings, undated (Box 1085, Folder 18)